<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<doxygen xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="compound.xsd" version="1.8.11">
  <compounddef id="compile_windows_mingw" kind="page">
    <compoundname>compile_windows_mingw</compoundname>
    <title>Building Portaudio for Windows with MinGW</title>
    <detaileddescription>
<sect1 id="compile_windows_mingw_1comp_mingw1">
<title>Portaudio for Windows With MinGW</title>
<para><emphasis>The following document is still being reviewed</emphasis></para><para>= MinGW/MSYS =</para><para>From the [<ulink url="http://www.mingw.org">http://www.mingw.org</ulink> MinGW projectpage]:</para><para>MinGW: A collection of freely available and freely distributable Windows specific header files and import libraries, augmenting the GNU Compiler Collection, (GCC), and its associated tools, (GNU binutils). MinGW provides a complete Open Source programming tool set which is suitable for the development of native Windows programs that do not depend on any 3rd-party C runtime DLLs.</para><para>MSYS: A Minimal SYStem providing a POSIX compatible Bourne shell environment, with a small collection of UNIX command line tools. Primarily developed as a means to execute the configure scripts and Makefiles used to build Open Source software, but also useful as a general purpose command line interface to replace Windows cmd.exe.</para><para>MinGW provides a compiler/linker toolchain while MSYS is required to actually run the PortAudio configure script.</para><para>Once MinGW and MSYS are installed (see the [<ulink url="http://www.mingw.org/MinGWiki">http://www.mingw.org/MinGWiki</ulink> MinGW-Wiki]) open an MSYS shell and run the famous:</para><para><programlisting><codeline><highlight class="normal">./configure</highlight></codeline>
<codeline><highlight class="normal">make</highlight></codeline>
<codeline><highlight class="normal">make<sp/>install</highlight></codeline>
</programlisting></para><para>The above should create a working version though you might want to provide &apos;<ndash/>prefix=&lt;path-to-install-dir&gt;&apos; to configure.</para><para>&apos;./configure <ndash/>help&apos; gives details as to what can be tinkered with.</para><para><mdash/> Mikael Magnusson</para><para>To update your copy or check out a fresh copy of the source</para><para>[wiki:UsingThePortAudioSvnRepository SVN instructions]</para><para><mdash/> Bob !McGwier</para><para>Back to the Tutorial: <ref refid="tutorial_start" kindref="compound">PortAudio Tutorials</ref> </para></sect1>
    </detaileddescription>
  </compounddef>
</doxygen>
