<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<doxygen xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="compound.xsd" version="1.8.11">
  <compounddef id="compile_cmake" kind="page">
    <compoundname>compile_cmake</compoundname>
    <title>Creating MSVC Build Files via CMake</title>
    <detaileddescription>
<para>This is a simple &quot;How-to&quot; for creating build files for Microsoft Visual C++ via CMake and the CMakeLists.txt file</para><para><orderedlist>
<listitem><para>Install CMake if you haven&apos;t got it already ([<ulink url="http://www.cmake.org">http://www.cmake.org</ulink>], minimum version required is 2.8).</para></listitem><listitem><para>If you want ASIO support you need to D/L the ASIO2 SDK from Steinberg, and place it according to <ref refid="compile_windows_asio_msvc" kindref="compound">Building Portaudio for Windows with ASIO support using MSVC</ref></para></listitem><listitem><para>Run the CMake GUI application and browse to <bold>source files</bold> directory and <bold>build</bold> directory: a. The <bold>source files</bold> directory (<emphasis>&quot;Where is the source code&quot;</emphasis>) is where the portaudio CMakeLists.txt file is located. b. The <bold>build</bold> directory (<emphasis>&quot;Where to build the binaries&quot;</emphasis>) is pretty much anywhere you like. A common practice though is to have the build directory located <bold>outside</bold> the source files tree (a so called &quot;out-of-source build&quot;)</para></listitem><listitem><para>Click <emphasis>Configure</emphasis>. This will prompt you to select which build files to generate. <bold>Note</bold> Only Microsoft Visual C++ build files currently supported!</para></listitem><listitem><para>In the CMake option list, enable the PORTAUDIO_xxx options you need, then click <emphasis>Configure</emphasis> again (Note that after this there are no options marked with red color)</para></listitem><listitem><para>Click <emphasis>Generate</emphasis> and you&apos;ll now (hopefully) have your VS build files in your previously defined <bold>build</bold> directory.</para></listitem></orderedlist>
</para><para>Both ASIO and DirectX SDK are automatically searched for by the CMake script, so if you have DirectX SDK installed and have placed the ASIO2 SDK according to point 2 above, you should be able to build portaudio with !DirectSound and ASIO support.</para><para>Should you later on decide to change a portaudio option, just jump in at step 5 above (MSVC will then prompt you to reload projects/solutions/workspace)</para><para><mdash/> Robert Bielik</para><para>Back to the Tutorial: <ref refid="tutorial_start" kindref="compound">PortAudio Tutorials</ref> </para>    </detaileddescription>
  </compounddef>
</doxygen>
